<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Trafford in Lancashire at the mariage of a daughter of the right worshipfull Sir Edmond Trafforde Knight, the 6. of September Anno. 1586. By William Massie bacheler in diuinity, and fellow of Brasennose Colledge in Oxforde</title>
            <author>Massie, William, d. 1610.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1586</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07233</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17631</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105628</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841355</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841355</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5932</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07233)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5932)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 574:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Trafford in Lancashire at the mariage of a daughter of the right worshipfull Sir Edmond Trafforde Knight, the 6. of September Anno. 1586. By William Massie bacheler in diuinity, and fellow of Brasennose Colledge in Oxforde</title>
                  <author>Massie, William, d. 1610.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ioseph Barnes, and are to be solde [in London by T. Cooke] in Paules Church-yard at the signe of the Tigres head,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1586.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Bookseller's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5932:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5932:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED AT TRAFFORD IN LANCASHIRE AT THE MARIAGE OF A DAVGHTER OF THE right Worſhipfull Sir ED<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MOND TRAFFORDE Knight, the 6. of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember Anno. 1586.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM MASSIE bacheler in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinity, and fellow of Braſennoſe Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in Oxforde.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prouer. 19.14.</bibl>
               <p>Houſe and riches are the inheritance of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but a godly wife commeth of the Lorde.</p>
            </q>
            <p>AT OXFORD. Printed by <hi>IOSEPH BARNES,</hi> and are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be ſolde in Paules Church-yard at the ſigne of the Tigres head, 1586.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5932:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5932:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FVL HIS VERY GOOD PATRONE SIR <hi>EDMVND TRAFFORD</hi> KNIGHT W. M. wiſheth health and long life in this woorlde, and in the next to come aeternall foelicity.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Hauing (right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) receaued by your good means, great courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies both in the country &amp; at my ſtudie in Oxforde, and as not able any way to requite the like, I haue yet and will ſtill keepe the ſame in a gratefull memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. In the meane time at a good teſtimonie hereof I dedicate this Sermon to your Worſhip, which at your requeſt I preached at your houſe before the right honorable the moſt noble Earle of Darby, and the right reuerend father in God the B. of Cheſter with diuerſe Knightes and Eſquires of great Woorſhip at the ſolemne marriage of your daughter, a modeſt and vertuous Gentlewoman, maried to a yong Gentleman of great worſhip and good education. The which holie ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage God bleſſe euen as he bleſſed Ioſeph,
<note place="margin">Gen. 48.20.</note> that it maie be ſaid of their iſſue as it was ſaid of his children, God make them as Ephraim and Manaſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>For your ſelfe as you haue long beene a principal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector of Gods trueth and a great countenance and credit to the Preachers therof in thoſe quarters, and haue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out and vnke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neled thoſe ſlie and ſubtil foxes the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites and ſeminarie Prieſts out of their c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lles &amp; caues,
<pb facs="tcp:5932:3"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rmoſt of your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, with the great ill will of many both open and priuat enemies to the prince and the Church, but your rewarde it with the Lord: and as you haue maintained ſtil yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> houſe with great hoſpitality in no point dim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing the glory of your woorthy predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, but rather adding to it: So I pray God ſtil continue your zeale, your liberality, your loyaltie and fidelitie to your prince, Church and common wealth, that here you may line long with encreaſe of worſhip, and after the race of your life welr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e here you maie be partaker of choſe vnſpeakeable ioies in the kingdome of Heauen which be prepared for all the elect children of God, vnto whoſe bleſſed protection I recommend you and al yours. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours to command in Chriſt Ieſu. WILLIAM MASSIE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:5932:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>The text, Pſal. 128.</bibl>
                  <p n="1">1 BLeſſed is euery one that feareth the Lorde and walketh in his waies &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 When thou eateſt the labours of thine handes thouſhalt bee bleſſed, and it ſhalbe well with thee.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Thy wife ſhall bee as the fruitefull vine on the ſides of thine houſe,</p>
                  <p n="4">4 And thy children like the oliue plantes round about thy table.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Loe ſurely thus ſhall the man bee bleſſed that feareth the Lorde.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 The Lorde out of Sion bleſſe thee, that thouſee the wealth of Hieruſalem all the daies of thy life.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 Yea that thou ſee thy childrens, &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE fit opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of this time, this great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>courſe of all ſortes haue moued me to take this text, and to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to entreat of the honorable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of mariage before this honorable and worſhipful aſſembly: wherein if you couſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the antiquity thereof, God appointed it before the fal of Adam in paradiſe: if you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb facs="tcp:5932:4"/>the neceſſity, it is naturall, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore agreeable to all eſtates: if you ſeeke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter comfort, then <hi>virtus vnita fortior,</hi> it is not good, man ſhould bee alone. If you care for delectation in an honeſt matter, then of all bonds and loues none is ſo delectable, none is ſo inuiolable as is the bond &amp; loue betwixt the husband &amp; the wife. Laſtly if you marke the continuation therof from elder times to theſe our preſent daies, then behold our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uior did honor mariage with his honorable preſence;
<note place="margin">Ioh. cap. 2.</note> and with his firſt moſt glorions miracle. The godly learned in al ages of all degrees at al times both princes the nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and gentility the ſtate eccleſiaſticall, the people, as Moſes, Aaron, Dauid, Eli, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel, Eſay, Zachary, and al the Apoſtles but Iohn, the auncient fathers, and reuerend bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in the pure and primitiue times, as Tertullian, Hilary, Nazianzen, Spiridion, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> others haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended, allowed and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed the ſame, neither to the hinderance of their functions nor detriment of the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth, nor the derogation of the glory of God.
<note place="margin">Iuelapol.</note> All which haue beene by our men both by penne, and in the pulpit proued ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally by ſcriptures, ſufficiently by fathers, &amp; perſpicuouſly by ancient hiſtories, wherof to diſcourſe more fully I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not, but wil conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb facs="tcp:5932:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>my ſelf with a ſhort compendious enarratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and explication of this text, wherein I note theſe two things. Firſt a deſcription of the husband, the wife and children with their fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall and ſinguler dueties. Secondly a peticion or prayer for them.</p>
            <p>Firſt in the deſcription of the hitsband the firſt and chiefeſt quality wherewith hee muſt bee adorned and furniſhed is,
<note place="margin">1. Part.</note> to feare god, to ſerue him aright, to haue a right &amp; a righteous faith, which muſt be grounded on the woord of God. Let me ſpeake as I haue read, and I do beleeue as I ſpeake: I would haue this husband whom I deſcribe to be a proteſtant, &amp; to mary a proteſtant. I would haue them both to be of one religion, and to be of a ſound religion, which I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded is not the ſtubborn obſtinacy of the Iew nor the Godleſſe impietie of the Turke, nor the vain ſuperſtition of the Papiſt, but is the ancient catholick &amp; apoſtolick faith which is now both preached by vs &amp; profeſſed by you, that is to beleeue rightly, to liue vprightly, to offer the ſweetince<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe of our praiers to god aboue, ſteedfaſtly to beleeue to be ſaued only by Chriſts death without any merit of ours, to frequent the church, to receaue the Lords ſupper in both kinds, to honor &amp; obey Rings &amp; Princes as the moſt noble and excellent in
<pb facs="tcp:5932:5"/>their dominions, and in a word to fear God Such a reuerend and religious fear had A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham ouer his ſonne Iſaack to mary him not to a prophane gentile or heatheniſh wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<note place="margin">Gen. 2.3.</note> but one of his owne ſtocke and lyneall diſcent, that ſerued &amp; worſhipped the ſame true God that he did: Thus doth the bleſſed Apoſtle teach,
<note place="margin">Cor. 6.14.</note> we muſt not drawe the yoke with infidels. For betwixt this godly huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and vertuous wife, there muſt be an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality in years and in vertues, both young or both old, and no meane loue ſoone hotte ſoone cold, but a moſt ardent and feruent loue which cannot be quenched with a flud of waters, which cannot bee without this fear of God, and except they bee of the ſame religion,
<note place="margin">Ambroſe.</note> for ſo defendeth Ambroſe: <hi>Inter quos eſt diuerſareligio, inter eos non eſt firma a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micitia.</hi> Thoſe that be of a contrary religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the loue betwixt them is not ſincere nor can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be of any long continuance. Many erre notoriouſly in their marriages through their careles contempt of this fear of God. Some mary in their noneage and minority, ſome reſpect onely beauty, others harken after lands, others after gold and ſiluer, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Poet:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O ciues ciues quare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da pecunia primum, vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus poſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> And many one for land takes
<pb facs="tcp:5932:5"/>a foole by the hand. Others are not aſhamed to holde this vile and villanous opinion, as prophane Atheiſtes, Agood marriage if the wife were away. But are we ſtronger than Sampſon, wiſer than Salomon, greater than Achab to tempt the Lord, who all moſt grieuouſly offended in this point? Sampſon was thereby diſhonored, Salomon brought ſo far through idolatrous women from this fear of God, that ſome of the auncient fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers doubt of his ſaluation. Ring Achab of himſelfe was ſolde to all miſchiefe, but was made the worſe through the wicked counſel of his vngratious wife Ieſabel:
<note place="margin">1 King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.22.</note> but they both had their tragical ends and well deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: a terrible ſpectacle for the like to al po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity. Theſe worldly marriages are iuſtly refuted by him who ſaide, <hi>Mallem virum pecunia, quàm pecunia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> viro indigentem.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Themiſt. offic.</hi> 2.</note> Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is an honeſt poore man than a wicked rich man. And thoſe fooliſh marriages are forbid by the wiſe man in his booke Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticus, Marrie thy Daughter,
<note place="margin">Cap. 7.25.</note> and ſo ſhalt thou perfourme a weightie matter: but giue her vnto a man of vnderſtanding. Glaucus in Homer preferred copper be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Goolde,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hom. Iliad.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> whereby hee ſhewed his follie. Martha choſe the woorſer part,
<note place="margin">Luk. 10.41.</note> whereby ſhee ſhewed her woorldelineſſe.
<pb facs="tcp:5932:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:5932:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:5932:7"/>Eſau preferred a meſſe of delicate broth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his birthright, for the which he is called of the Apoſtle a prophane man.
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.16.</note> So many prefer beutie before bounty, riches before vertue, gold and ſiluer before ſhamefaſtneſſe and godlines, lands and inheritances before honeſty and diſcretion. But this our religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous husband muſt feare the Lorde with a Godly feare,
<note place="margin">Ioſ. 24.15.</note> like the good ſonne of Ioſua who hath this bleſſed teſtimony that he fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the lord with his whole family.
<note place="margin">Pro. 1.7.</note> For this fear of the Lord is the beginning of al wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.
<note place="margin">Luk. 18.2.</note> As for thoſe men that reſemble the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous iudge, that neither feare God, nor good man, that neuer thinke of the ſaluation of their ſinful ſeduced ſoules, that either be Athieſtes or Libertines or Machiuelians or Spend-thriftes or couetous Nabals or great Gamſters or Luxurious and Riotous perſons or ſeditious and traiterous papiſts, are no fitte men to bee ſuch a husband as I propoſe. But ſuch I commend as here out Prince and Prophet, in royalty a Prince, in learning a Prophet,
<note place="margin">Mat. 10.28.</note> doth, who fear not men that can kill the body, but fear the Lord who can kill both body and ſoule, and caſt both into hell fire, euen ſuch a one as walkes not in the waies of the wicked or in his owne waies, but in the waies of the Lorde, which
<pb facs="tcp:5932:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>is the ſecond qualitie and duety of a good &amp; Godly busband.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>And walkes in his waies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond quality of this husband is to walke in the water of the Lorde, wherein I may decipher vnto you the wit and wiſdome of a godly and religious husband.
<note place="margin">1. Cor 9.24.</note> Our life is aptly reſembled to a race or courſe or a iourney, in going whereof a man muſt haue a wiſe and expert guide to direct him in his iourney. This guide of our religion of our life of all our actions is the woorde of God. For ſo our Prophet erclaimeth with a zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous exclamation, vſing a retoricall ſubtec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on both playing the opponent &amp; reſpondent himſelfe.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.9.</note> O wherewith ſhall a yong man learne to redreſſe and reforme his waies: Euen by ruling himſelfe according to thy woorde. This worde is a rule to iudge the ſtraight from the crooked, a ſquire to direct our building by, a compaſſe to guide our ſhippe by, a Law to iudge controuerſies by, and as a God in this world to decide and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine all matters which ſhall ariſe in the Churches of God, euen to the end of the world. For our purpoſe the Iewes erred in marriage they would ſeeke a diuorſe for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery trifle, they would marry wiues that were yong, faire, &amp; wealthy, and when they
<pb facs="tcp:5932:8"/>were either old or poore or deformed, they would put them away. They did alſo make the Church of God a denue of theeues by their prophane ſelling and buieng in it: but our ſauiour reforms theſe notorious errors by two principles:
<note place="margin">Mat. 19.8.</note> the one is, It was not ſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning:
<note place="margin">Mat. 21.13.</note> the other, It is writ, my houſe ſhalbe called the houſe of praier. And certainly this husband ſhal ſhewe his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in this, if he guide himſelfe, his wife and family according to this rule, to walke in the waies of the Lorde, which are fully and faithfully ſette downe in the olde and newe Teſtament,
<note place="margin">Ier. 8.9.</note> for ſo the prophet think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, You thinke you are a wiſe people, but you reiect the Lawe of God, and what wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome can be in you? And Auſten cites out of Iob,
<note place="margin">Enchirid. ad Laur. c. 2</note> this ſentence, <hi>Hominis Sapientia eſt pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas.</hi> The Godly man is the wiſe man. This wiſe husband may learne in this woorde to loue his wife entirely,
<note place="margin">Pro. 5.18.</note> to be merry with her in the Lord, to abſtaine from too much bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe,
<note place="margin">Col. 3.19.</note> to dwell with her according to knowledge, not to bee rigorous but courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous towardsher, for w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the moſt, courteous perſwaſions preuail more than ſharp repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions doe. But chiefly his wiſedome ſhal appeare in this, to bring to his houſe no ill, naughty &amp; defamed perſons. So Menelaus
<pb facs="tcp:5932:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>did fondely in entertaining to his houſe friendely that lewed and laſciuious Parts, whereby his wife faire Helena was defiled, as alſo he muſt be ſufferable in the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities of his wife. For as a litle iarre in muſick is not eaſily eſpied, ſo a litle ſhrewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the wife may be colerated.
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.7.</note> For this cauſe Saint Peter would haue houſe bands to honour their wiues, which conſiſtes in this, in prouiding ſufficiently for their neceſſities by a godly prouidence, &amp; to beare with their infirmities in the Lord,
<note place="margin">Prou. 29.18 Eccle. 9.</note> and in no wiſe, a wiſe houſeband may bee iealous ouer the honeſty of his wife, for that either needes not, or bootes not. Ouely let him hee as zealous in religion, as wiſe in his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement of himſelfe, his wife and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: ſo let him auoide idleneſſe, and labour diligently in his vocation, which is the third quality of a good houſeband.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>When thou eateſt the labours of thine owne hands thou ſhalt bee bleſſed, and it ſhalbe well with thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This good husband muſt not be idle and ſlothfull, but labor faithfully &amp; painefully in that vocation wherein God hath called him.
<note place="margin">Gen. 2.15.</note> So Adam before his fall had this charge of God to dreſſe the garden of Eden.
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note> And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his fall this precept, In the ſweate
<pb facs="tcp:5932:9"/>of thy brows thou ſhalt eate thy bread. The diuine Philoſopher Plato ſawe ſo much by the inſtinct of nature <hi>Nemo ſibi naſcitur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cic. Offic.</hi> 1.</note> wee are borne to defend our Country to benefit and gratifie our friendes and neighbours. There be foure parts in the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth. The Prince as the head, the honorable and woorſhipfull, as armes and ſhoulders, the ſtate eccleſiaſtical as eies, the common mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude as the feete. O bleſſed and happie ſhall that realme be when theſe foure partes agree in a ſweete conſort and melody in the amiable and bleſſed loue of peace and vnity, diſcharging their duties fully and faithfully in the feare of God. The Prince in appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the nobility and gentry in counſelling, the preachers in feeding, and the people in beying.
<note place="margin">2. King. 18.</note> For Princes, the imitation of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid of Ezechias of Ioſias is worth the imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, who al were very diligent in appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting good lawes for the religion of God, and alſo I may not forget the great zeal &amp; lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Alphred king of this la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,
<note place="margin">Act. and Mon.</note> who diuided the day into three parts, ſome hours he took for his priuat ſtudy &amp; ſeruice of god, ſome he reſerued for the hearing of matters of ſtate and the common wealth, and the reſt he left for his reſt, repaſt and recreation. For coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers they may imitate Ioſeph, who vnder
<pb facs="tcp:5932:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>king Pharao ruled the land of Aegypt with great and ſingular wiſdom and prouidence,
<note place="margin">Gen. 41.39.</note>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 44.5.</note> &amp; they muſt bee as Daniel was to Darius, in whom the enemies coulde finde no fault touching the gouernment of his kingdome. For the Clergy to feede by preaching by hoſpitality by godlines of life,
<note place="margin">Humfred de vita Iuel.</note> to follow that reuerend Biſhop of Salisbury, who follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed the noble emperour who ſaid, O where ſhould a captaine die but in the fielde: ſo his poeſy was, O where ſhould a Biſhop die but in the pulpit? For where preaching faileth there the people periſheth.
<note place="margin">Prou. 29.18 Rom. 13.12.</note> For the common people they muſt be obedient to their Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat to loue and honor their Prince, to bear that nature and affection to their ſoueraign as did the Iſraelites to Dauid the king of Iſrael, who al made this noble proteſtation, It is better that a thouſand of vs dy than Dauid our king. God ſaue Dauid the king, if hee die the great light of Iſrael is quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched: So let al faithful and loyal ſubiectes beare this affection to our moſt noble and gracious Princeſſe Elizabeth.
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 18.3.</note> It is better that a thouſand of vs die by the ſeditious treacheries of our falſe forſworne and frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulent countrimen than Elizabeth our Queene. God protect and preſerue Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth: If ſhee die and miſcarie the great
<pb facs="tcp:5932:10"/>light of Iſraell ſhall be quenched.</p>
            <p>Now if our husband be any of theſe four, he hath ſomething to doe, he muſt be careful to prouide for his houſe, to feede &amp; cloth his family, to inſtruct his wife and children, to pay his ſeruants their wages faithfully and truely, and to walke in that vocation with a good conſcience whereto God hath called him.
<note place="margin">Ari. oecom. lib. 1. cap. 6.</note> The office of the husband, is to get, the duery of the wife is to keepe: the office of the husband is honeſlly to maintaine his liueli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, the duty of the wife is, prudently to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne the houſehould. Such a noble care had the noble Emperor Valerianus of whome thus it is writ,
<note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. 7. cap. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Aula Valeriani erat referta pijs viris, &amp; Eccleſia Dei facta eſt.</hi> The court of Valerianus the Emperour was fraught and furniſhed with godly men, and made the Church of God. Such a noble Captaine was Cornelius who hath this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port to feare the Lorde with his whole fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily.
<note place="margin">Act. 10.1.2.</note> Thus if our husband labor in his vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation he ſhal haue this blesſing of the Lord to eate the fruites of his own labours.
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.</note> The moſt noble and learned King Salomon in thoſe <hi>12.</hi> Chapters of his book Eccleſiaſtes declares moſt largely and learnedly how all things vnder the cope of heauen are nothing but griefe, ſorowe, vexation &amp; anguiſh, griefe
<pb facs="tcp:5932:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>of body, ſorrow of hart, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ix<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion of braine, and anguiſh of mind: but yet this to bee our part and portion and a bleſſing of God in this life, when wee both ſow and trape, when we both plant the vine and drink the vine, when we build houſes and dwell therein, when we can be content to liue of our owne, for that is our owne that doth vs good, when we eat &amp; drink without gluttony and drunkennes, in ſobriety and modeſty in the fear of God. This is a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, this is a great bleſſing, this is a great and gracious bleſſing of God himſelfe, and ſuch a bleſſing ſhal this religious and wiſe &amp; politick husband enioy, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue deſcribed to you: wherin becauſe I haue bin longer than either perhaps I ſhould or you expected, I wil be the ſhorter in the deſcription of the wife and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Which thus foloweth in the Text.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Thy wife ſhall bee as the fruitful vine on the ſides of thine houſe, &amp; thy children like the oliue plants round about thy table.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Among the trees that be fertil and fruitful the Oliue is commended for his fatnes,
<note place="margin">Iudg 9.9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> the fig tre for his ſweetnes, the vine for cheerfulnes, for wine driues away ſorrow, &amp; is a ſouerain reſtoratiue for an heauy and penſiue hart: ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all creatures men and weomen be only commended for their learning, wiſdom &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines. The compariſon of a woman to the vine
<pb facs="tcp:5932:11"/>I wil not amplify largely but touch it briefly. Firſt the vine is weak,
<note place="margin">Plin. lib. 4.</note> &amp; muſt be vnderſet and vnderpropped by ſome ſure and ſtrong ſtay: ſo the wife is the weaker veſſell more ſubiect to infirmities, &amp; a wiſe modeſt man wil not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe hir infirmities, but tolerat the ſame with good diſcretion:
<note place="margin">2. Sa. 11.1.7.</note> ſo Berſabe was more beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful than ſtrong, when ſhe defiled hir body with Dauid, brake her faith and loue with hir good husband Vrias: which was the very occaſion of his death. Eua the mother of all ſhewed her ſelfe very weak when ſhee was beguiled with an aple.
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.6.</note>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 19.26.</note> Lots wife was both weak &amp; wicked, when ſhe looked back in token ſhe luſted after Sodoma and Gomorra againſt the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God, but ſhe was turned into a piller of ſalt: a terrible ſpectacle &amp; moſt horrible mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument of wicked back-ſliders and ſinful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolters,
<note place="margin">Plinie. l. 14.</note> to al godly poſterity. Secondly a vine is not only weak but low too, it growes near the earth: So a godly wife muſt not be proud and ſtately in her owne conceits, but humble &amp; modeſt in the preſence of her husband. For a godly wife neither muſt nor will ſeek a ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty or ſuperiority ouer her husband.
<note place="margin">Lomb. lib. 4</note> For the woman (as the maſter of the ſentences doth allegoriſe) was made of the rib of man, that he ſhould entreat her gently as his mate: ſhe was neither made of the head, that ſhe ſhould vſurp
<pb facs="tcp:5932:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>autority &amp; power ouer him, nor yet of the feete that ſhe ſhuld be abuſed as a ſlaue &amp; vile ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by him: And euen as the loweſt ſoils be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly moſt battle and fertil, ſo thoſe wee men that be moſt modeſt &amp; humble, are meſt filled &amp; furniſhed with gods gifts &amp; graces,
<note place="margin">Iam. 4.6.</note> euen in the greateſt meaſure. For as the holy ſcripture ſaith, god reſiſteth the proud,
<note place="margin">Plin. l. 14.</note> &amp; giueth grace to the hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble. Thirdly the vine is fruitful, it be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth grapes plentifully, which wel ripened, &amp; mightily preſſed, do yeeld great ſtore of wine,
<note place="margin">Galen. de. Sa. 4.</note> which cheereth the hart of man, refreſheth the vital ſpirits, heateth the cold ſtomack, helpeth the rawnes and crudity &amp; many other infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the ſame. Ther are many wiues which are fruitful in children, and this is a corporall bleſſing: for ſo many godly children, ſo many bleſſings of God. In the old law ſterrility and barrennes was deemed as a curſe of God, and therefore many godly &amp; religious weomen as Sara, Rachel, Rebecca,
<note place="margin">Gen. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Anna w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> others har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily &amp; hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly prayed of god, that he would giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> children.
<note place="margin">Pſal 127.5.</note> O happy &amp; bleſſed is the man that hath his quiuer ful of godly children brought vp in the fear of the lord, they ſhal be a terror to the enimy, a ſtay to the country, &amp; a comfort to their parents. But ther is another ſpiritual bleſſing,
<note place="margin">Good reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</note> ther is another fruitfulnes beeter tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this, that is, that the wife be inueſted &amp; ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:5932:12"/>with good qualities. Firſt that ſhe feare God religiouſly, &amp; walk in his waies, for then ſhal God procure &amp; purchaſe hir fauor &amp; grace in the eies of her husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. And therfore we find by experience that diuers weomen not ſo fair being godly, are better liked and loued of their husbands, than others more amiable &amp; beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful,
<note place="margin">Plinie.</note> and yet not ſo godly. For as the loadſtone draweth hard yron to it: ſo this fear of god in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wife wil eaſily moue a wiſe husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: but it wil force a waiward husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to entreat hit louing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; gently.
<note place="margin">Loue.</note> And as to ſeaſon vnſauery meats, pleaſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; delicat ſauces be prepared: ſo to giue a good reliſh to the ſweet food of honeſt mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age it muſt be tempered &amp; ſeaſoned w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a moſt ardent &amp; feruent loue. And good reaſon to loue them to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue giuen our bodies and al, and choſen to bee partakers of all ioies and ſorrows, of wealth and wo, of health &amp; ſicknes, &amp; for who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we forſake father, mother, brother, ſiſter, frind, kif &amp; kin &amp; al, &amp; that not for a time, but during y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> courſe of our life. I ſay it is good reaſon we ſhould like &amp; loue them, &amp; that with a moſt near &amp; dear affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. We read of noble Iulia Pompeys wife, who expreſſed the ſigne of a moſt louing wife, for being w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> child, when ſhe ſaw her husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds warlick coat brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the city al imbrued with gored bloud, fel in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſudden ſound, ſcriching moſt rufully and
<pb facs="tcp:5932:12"/>wofully crieng out. O Pompey Pompey fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel, and ſo this noble lady with her vntimely child preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly dyed. The greateſt maintainer of this houeſt loue is ſhamefaſtneſſe,
<note place="margin">Shamefaſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> which is ſuch a vertue in a woman, that without it the reſt are al diſgraced. For this ſhamefaſtnes is giuen to weomen, for a defence to keepe their reputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for a caſtle to preſerue their chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, for a fort to maintain their honor, and for a garland to aduance their prayſe and comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Ariſtotle the famous philoſopher re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiers in a mayd to bee mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed foure thinges, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, riches, good pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage, beauty &amp; vertue. Beauty is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable, a good parentage is honorable, wealth, land &amp; a good inheritaunce is not to bee contemned: but the chiefeſt dowry, the beſt inheritance, the moſt pretious Iewell in a woman is vertue, &amp; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the vertue of obedience. So our Apoſtle teacheth, Wiues obay your husbands.
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5 22. Obedience</note> Man is fitter for this ſoueraynty of rule &amp; regunent then a woman, euen by the lawe of nature, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing greater ſkill to rule, experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to gouern, capacity to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehend, wiſdome to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth to execute, carefulnes to proſecute, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to ſuffer, and a greater courage and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimity to performe and perfect all purpoſes and practiſes whatſoeuer.
<note place="margin">Hoſt. 1.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> In the booke of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter wee reade of king Haſueroſh king of the
<pb facs="tcp:5932:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>Medes &amp; Perſians, he had a maſterly and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perious ſhrewe to his wife Queen Vaſti, who would not obay him in a certayne matter. Whervpon he called and conue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted his nobles and counſellours and by their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell ſhe was put away, and hee maried the noble and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous lady Queene Heſter. But let this imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Oueene goe. Let vs paſſe ouer Zantippe Soccates wife.
<note place="margin">Exod. 4. lob. 2.9.</note> Let Sipora Moſes wife, let Iobs wife and good Tobias alſo, as moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and notorious ſhrewes goe, and let euery godly wife follow the good example of godly Sara, who obeyed her huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with all dutifull reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and called him Lord in toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of her ſingular humility.
<note place="margin">Good name.</note> And as ſhe muſt be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient, ſo ſhe muſt haue an eſpecial care of hir good name. For a good name is as a ſweete oyntment and as a moſt delicious &amp; precious perfume.
<note place="margin">Plutarch in Caeſar.</note> Ceſar wold haue his wife Pompeia not only fre from diſhoneſty, but alſo fre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al ſuſpicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both of diſhoneſty &amp; diſloyalty. There be many waies to preſerue this good name, but I take this to be as one moſt chiefe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in a maid or wife to be reſident at home, as the ſnaile,
<note place="margin">Tit. cap. 2.5.</note> &amp; not oft to range &amp; run abroad as Dina did.
<note place="margin">To keepe home.</note> For by this means the houſe ſhal be better gouerned, her husband better plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, all euill ſuſpicions auoyded, and great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences ſaued. For fewe there be but they are
<pb facs="tcp:5932:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>great waſters in their gay and gorgeous ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel, which is the more encreaſed by goſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and gadding abroad as the manner is in ſome places. But our Apoſtle teacheth godly weome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not to delite in too gay and gariſh ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel,
<note place="margin">1 Pet 3. 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2.9.</note> but ſo to attire themſelues as wel beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth modeſt matrons, and as is fitteſt for the vocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their husbands. And here our king and propher Oauid in modeſty a prophet, in maieſty a king would haue a godly wife to be as a ſide &amp; part of the houſe, or as a wall to the houſe to defend it, not to bee a ruine to pull it down, either by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pride of her fancies, or pomp of her train, or delicatnes of her dyet, or ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſnes in Iewels, or brauery in apparel, or lightnes in conuerſation, to roote vp the wals of her houſe, to turne vp al topſituruy, and not to leaue one ſtone vpon another.</p>
            <p>Now if the godly wife bee as the fruitfull vine, or fat floriſhing oliue, no maruaile if her children bee finely and fitly reſembled to the braunches of the vine or tender plants of the oliue tree. The braunche is tender, it wil bend or bowe at your pleaſure, the yong children be pliable as ſoft waxe, they be flerible as tender oliue branches, then a gentle rod wil break no bones,
<note place="margin">Prou. cap. Ephe. 6.4.</note> then he that ſpares the rod doth ſpil &amp; ſpoile the childe. For this is the exhortation of S. Paul, you Parents bring vp your childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:5932:14"/>in the faith and fear of the lord, get you ſchool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters both to inſtruce them by doctrine and reforme them by diſcipline. For a child better vnborn than vntaught.
<note place="margin">Ariſt. pol. l. 8. cap. 3.</note> The old Grecians (as the noble philoſopher ſaith) were wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to teach their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 3. things <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. the which thus the fine &amp; ingenious poet hath expreſſed,
<note place="margin">In Eunuch.</note> 
               <hi>Facpericulum in literis, in palaeſtra, in muſica.</hi> They were trained vp in the liberal &amp; ingenious arts, as chiefely Grammar, Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick, &amp; Muſick, &amp; in feats of actiuity, whereby their bodies were made the ſtronger to abide tough &amp; long ſtudy the better.
<note place="margin">Pro. 22.6.</note> And king Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who was diligently taught of Nathan the prophet giues forth this precept &amp; profit, teach a child in his youth vertu &amp; learning, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he coms to years he wil not forget it.
<note place="margin">Act 7.22.</note> So Moſes, ſo Dantel, ſo Samuel, ſo Paul, ſo Timothy, ſo Origen were trained vp from their infancy both in diuine learning,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.</note> and moſt of them alſo in prophane literature. The fruit ſhalbe this, as S. Ciril ſaith,
<note place="margin">Contra Iu. lib. 7.</note> 
               <hi>pueri ſacris literis enutriti, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtea fiunt religioſisſimt,</hi> children nouſled &amp; nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp from their tender yeares in reading and hearing holy Scriptures, they ſhal reape this fruite thereby not to be ſuperſtitious or hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal in opinions, or hauty and lofty in ſpirite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, but to be moſt religious, &amp; as the king of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el ſaw, They wil reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber ſuch things as they
<pb facs="tcp:5932:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>learn in their youth,
<note place="margin">Pro. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the better whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they come to years of diſcretion. And as in battle it is a neceſſary point &amp; poll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y for the getting of the victory &amp; conqueſt euer our enimies, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one ſoldiar is ſlain, that another preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly take his ſtation and place &amp; therein fight manfullie and coragiouſly ſo in the good geueinment of a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a good father dieth ſome learned and wiſe men take it to be a neceſſary point &amp; pollicy for the mantenance &amp; preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of peace &amp; vnity againſt eiull diſſention &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpiracy, that y ſon take his place if he be able to weald &amp; dicharge the like functio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; veretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Loe ſurely thus ſhal the man be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that feareth the Lorde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This religious fear of God which brings to the husband wife &amp; children both temporall &amp; ſpirituall bleſſings both in this life and in the life to come, doth conſiſt in following vertues, &amp; forſaking vices: which muſt be with al care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe auoided. Now the noyſome and poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonful weedes which will hurt both husband, wife &amp; childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, muſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al diligence be grubbed out of the grounds of our harts, leaſt the vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous &amp; contagious weeds ſtifle &amp; ouer-grow the good &amp; pure corn. The weedes be the ſin of Sodom &amp; Bomorra, polygamy, inceſt, adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, fornication, al vncleannes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon gaming, riotous &amp; prodigal liuing, careleſſe ſecurity in
<pb facs="tcp:5932:15"/>the parents, &amp; ſtubborn contumacy in the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Theſe hainous &amp; horrible vyees, conſume our bodies, waſt our goods, ſhorten our liues, diſcredit our good names, make our enimies to mock vs, giue occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the papiſts to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme the name of god, &amp; the religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which we profeſſe, endanger the ſaluation of our ſinneful ſoules, and neuer eſcape the due &amp; dreadful pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhmentes of God either in this life,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.8. 2 Sam. 12.10 Gen. 9. Gen. 19.</note> or in the life to come. Take exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple by Dauid, the ſword of God did neuer depart from his houſe. By Noah, he was mocked of his own ſon. By Lot, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted inceſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his own daughters: by A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacleo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a noble poet, who was ſo famous a bib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of wine and ſtrong drinks, that he was cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with a huske of a grape. Take example of Eli an old iudge,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 2.22.</note> an old prieſt, &amp; an old father: &amp; of his two rebellious ſonnes Hophny &amp; Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nees, in the end the wicked &amp; luxurious ſonnes were killed in battle, one of their wiues died with child,
<note place="margin">Chap. 4.</note> theold father Ely fel backward fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſtool &amp; brake his necke, the arke of God was taken of the barbarous Philiſtines, &amp; the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry departed from Iſrael. For this purpoſe I haue read this excellent hiſtory. There came once before wiſe Solon a father with his ſon, one accuſing the other. The father complained of the diſobedience of his ſon: &amp; the ſon accuſed the father of his ill education, which was the
<pb facs="tcp:5932:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>cauſe of his diſobedience. Solon wel conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the cauſe, &amp; perceiuing a falt to be in both, did thus determine and decide the matter: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the father had not brought vp his ſon in good inſtruction, &amp; dutiful correction, therfore the father after his death ſhould be depriued of his ſepulcher: and the ſon for his diſobedience ſhould be diſinherited. You wil perhaps think this a ſharp iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of a wiſe &amp; graue iudge, but ſore diſeaſes need ſtrong medecins, and if Solons determinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were put in vre in theſe our daies, I feare me ſome fathers would lack the honor of their burial, &amp; ſome ſonnes would be put from their inheritance. But if the godly husband, wife &amp; children do auoid theſe noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious vices, if the husband be religious, wiſe &amp; laborious in his vocation, if the wife bee chaſt, modeſt, obedient &amp; hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble, if the children be wel ſchooled and brought vp in the faith and feare of the Lord: then they al ſhal be bleſſed both in the city and in the field,
<note place="margin">Deut. 24.</note> in the fruit of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, in the fruit of the ground, in their cattle, in their basket, in their comming in, &amp; in their going out: their Oxen ſhalbe ſtrong to labour,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 144.</note> their ſheep ſhal bring forth ten thouſand in the ſtreetes, they ſhall not go into captiuity, they ſhalbe bleſſed in al the labors of their hands, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as the trees of the lord ful of ſuck &amp; ſappe, as the trees planted by the waters ſide, they
<pb facs="tcp:5932:16"/>ſhalbe pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted in the houſe of the lord, they ſhall proſper and floriſh in their yong years, in their old age they ſhal be fatre, fat, and wel liking, yea they ſhal ſee the church of God floriſh, their children liue long, &amp; peace in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth. For the which 3. here our prophet and Prince Dauid prateth, which petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Dauid I wil ſhut vp briefly thus in the concluſion.</p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>The Lord out of Syon bleſſe thee that thou maiſt ſee the good of Ieruſalem all the dayes of thy lyfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>Yea that thou ſee thy childrens chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and peace vppon Iſraell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this praier of Dauid three circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are worth the due co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 1. who prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. A king and a prophet. 2. to whom he prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. To the Lorde that dwels in Sion. 3. for what. For three things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 For the proſperity of the Church.</item>
               <item>2 For the long liues of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maried parties.</item>
               <item>3 And for the peace of Iſrael, which I may well vnderſtand the common wealth.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Great is the efficacity and force of praier both in peace &amp; war, in proſperity and aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, in health and ſicknes at all times &amp; in al eſtates. It is ſayd, <hi>Orante Moſe vicit populus,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Moſes prayed for his people they va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quiſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed theyr enemies.
<note place="margin">Ioh. 5. Io. 14.16.13.</note> And this is our comfort that whatſoeuer we aſke of the father in Chriſtes
<pb facs="tcp:5932:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>name if it be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>medious &amp; expedient for vs, we ſhall be ſure to obtayne it. Then no meruell if here the prophet and king of Iſraell geue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelie to prayer. O it is a great matter and of great importance when princes and nobles &amp; men of great worſhip be religious and geuen to prayer &amp; to the holy ſeruice of God. For this cauſe Dauid was accounted a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after Gods owne heart.
<note place="margin">1 King. 20</note> For this cauſe Ioſtas that yong king is ſo highly commended. For this cauſe Ezechias his daies were prolonged 15 yeares lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger. This makes the church of god to grow vp luſtily as the palm tree and to floriſh as the tal Cedar of Libanus, the people euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſit quietly and peaceably vnder his own vine, and the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth to haue peace &amp; plentie as in the happy daies of Salomon. Ciril in an epiſtle to Cheodoſius euen in the beginning thus ſaith,
<note place="margin">Citil. Epiſt. ad I heod.</note> 
               <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etas in Deum eſt fundamentum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gijs honoribies.</hi> O noble emperour the ſtate of your common wealth hanges of your religion towards God. If you ſerue him aright your kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal floriſh, one of your royal ſeed ſhall alwaies ſit on your royal ſeate: but if you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake God he wil forſake you, hee wil raſe and root out your memories from the face of the earth, hee wil trample your name and fame vnder his feet, he wil eaſt your honors in the duſt, and this is a curſe of al curſes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5932:17"/>
            <p>The 2 circumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is, to whom he praieth: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the lord of Sion. Our prophet &amp; prince praieth not to Abraham, to Iſack, to Iacob, or to any archangel or angel in heauen, but to the lord which dwelled in Syon.
<note place="margin">Mat. 9. Ioh. 16.</note> We haue a plain co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement to pray to him alone, we haue a firme promiſe that ſo praying our praiers ſhal be hard: we haue the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of al godly men ſo to pray both in the old &amp; new teſtament. Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero reports of Ceſar thus, <hi>qui ad te non audent accedere Caeſar,
<note place="margin">Orat. pro Deiotar.</note> tuam humanitatem ignorant.</hi> They that be affrayd to ſpeak to thee o Ceſar, they know not thy ſingular humanity: ſo I ſay they that alleage eyther their owne indignity or the ſeuerity of god againſt ſinners, &amp; ſo dare not come to Ieſus alone by harty prayer, they know not his ſinguler humanity &amp; humility.</p>
            <p>The 3 circumſtaunce is the matter for the which our prophet praieth, which is threefold: for the church, the lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g liues of the maryed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, for the peace of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth. There be 2 deadly &amp; mortal enemies to the common wealth and church of god. Hereſy, &amp; treachery. The ſubtil ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in Geneſis did moue Adam and Eua to taſt of the forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tree,
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.4.</note> &amp; ſaid, you ſhall not dy: ſo the cruell and ſubtill ſerpent of Rome eggeth forward &amp; encorageth his ſworn vaſſals of Spain, France &amp; Italy &amp; our deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate diueliſh Engliſh rebels to aſſay to touch y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:5932:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>Lords anoynted and almes them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fayr golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> promiſes, you ſhall not by, you ſhall get you a name, you ſhal be men of great renowne. It is an heroical deſignment and meritorius before God and good catholicks.
<note place="margin">Iuel in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of letie.</note> A famous and moſt learned Biſhop of this land, doth hold there be four ordinary means to keep hereſy from our church, &amp; treaſon from our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth.


<label>1 Learning.</label> The firſt is to maintain vniuerſities &amp; free ſchools.


<label>2 Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</label> The ſecond is to appoint learned preachers in euery pariſh Church to catechiſe the youth,
to teach the people obedience.

<label>3 Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes.</label> The third to bee thankful to god for al his benefits.

<label>4 Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</label> The fourth diſcipline to reward the godly and puniſh the wicked. The execution of theſe thinges will make our church &amp; common wealth to floriſh; the contempt of theſe wil make our court as Sion the holy hil of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, our church as Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holy city of the lord,
<note place="margin">Luk. 19.</note> our land as Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea the holy land. Sion was, Ieruſalem was, Iudea was, but now Sio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is vtterly razed, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is vtterly ranſacked. Therefore let not Rome brag of any prerogatiue of her place for antiquity, or pallace for royalty. That which hapned to Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Rome great controuerſy there is betwixt the Ieſuits &amp; vs wher antichriſt ſhuld ſit, and who he is.
<note place="margin">Ad Did.</note> I wil ſay nothing of S. Ierom, only I wil cite one ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Bernard which ſhal make the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:5932:18"/>cleare. <hi>Ep.</hi> 125. <hi>Beſtia illa in apocalypſi cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> datumeſt os loque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s blasphemias, &amp; bellu gerere cum ſanctis,
<note place="margin">Be. ad Gau. de lorator.</note> petre cathedram occupat tanquam Leo paratus ad pradam.</hi> The beaſt ſpoken of in the Apocalyps to whom is giuen a mouth to ſpeak blaſphemies and to make war with ſaines, doth now occupy the ſeat of Peter as a Lion prepared to his pray. The place then for Antichriſt is the great city Babylo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<note place="margin">Roma. Septicollis.</note> ſited on ſeauen hils. The names of the hils he <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinus,
<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.</note> Capitolinus, Aùe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinus, Caelius, Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilinus, Viminalis, Quirinalis.</hi> Then for the perſon who is that great Antichriſt (if ye ty him to one perſon) then it muſt eyther bee the Turk, or y Iew, or the heathen emperor, or the Pope. But if Antichriſt eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the great antichriſt muſt ſit in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of god as god, if antichriſt muſt deceaue by falſe and fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulent miracles,
<note place="margin">Apoc. 18.</note> if antichriſt muſt be a falſe and fooliſh prophet as Balaam, if antichriſt muſt haue the name of miſtery writen in his forehead as once y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hyprieſt of the Iews had in his <hi>Lamina, ſanctit as ſehouae</hi> Holines to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, if antichriſt muſt ouercome by flattery, by ſweet &amp; ſugred ſpeaches as harlots doe, not by arms &amp; dint of ſword as cruel tyrants doe: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> where antichriſt ſhal ſit &amp; who anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt is, I refer it to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudgemets of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; conſciences of the godly that heare me this preſent day. <hi>To God the father. c&amp;.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
